Wie sprichst du mit der jüngeren Generationen im Kibbutz über das, was passiert ist?
Firstly,
as the person that was head of education at the kibbutz,
this was what I was doing
throughout the year-and-a-half after October 7,
it was,
firstly...
If you speak about the kibbutz,
kibbutz is like a community,
so the first thing we wanted to do is to make them feel,
like get them back on their feet after October 7th,
because they were in a very,
very bad situation...
We’re talking about children and teenagers,
and you have to understand,
that children and teenagers here,
some of them...
saw their parents or siblings
get shot and die in front of their eyes.
some of them...
there were four teenagers that were murdered
in the kibbutz.
There was one teenager that was kidnapped,
there was a child that was kidnapped,
there were families that were completely broken.
I can tell you about one teenager,
that...
when the head of security
came to his house in the morning...
he found there was a kid that was jogging.
October 7...
6:30 in the morning,
there was a kid that went jogging.
A twelve-and-a-half-year-old,
and the head of security went to find him,
and he didn’t have time to get him back to his house,
so he put him in his own house.
When he turned to get back to the battle,
he was
immediately murdered, it was a very brutal murder.
we know because it took us days to identify the body.
And...
apparently there was a teenager that...
saw the entire thing.
The entire murder through the shutters of her house,
it took us five months to understand
why she doesn’t leave the house
where she was evacuated to.
So the...
the stories of the teenagers, they were in shock,
they were in complete shock.
And what did we do in order to give them the...
When you speak about the kibbutz,
you speak about the community,
when you are a part of a group,
when you have a sense of belonging to a group,
this is a very
essential element for your
recovery from the trauma.
A strong group gives you strong resilience.
So, we really started
on creating that community within them.
we made,
the kibbutz that we were evacuated to,
Mishmar HaEmek, gave us.
the facilities we needed and we just...
they gave us this empty
bomb shelter which looked horrible at the beginning,
but many people came to help,
the people of Mishmar HaEmek are amazing people really.
Many people from there,
and from the surrounding areas came to help,
and we painted and
we made a little nice
warm club for them.
The best we could under the circumstances.
It was unbelievable to see.
As time went by it became their little sanctuary,
they used to come back from school,
Go,
because each family got a small room,
imagine me with my husband,
with my two children with my two dogs in a...
maybe 5 by 5...
unit.
5 meters,
really small.
And teenagers need their privacy,
so they couldn’t find their...
They couldn’t find the place where they could feel,
the quiet they need as teenagers,
and it was unbelievable to see
they used to come back from school,
grab a blanket and go to the club and they would
fall asleep on the sofas,
with other friends...
And they would
Take a nap or...
come and play a nice game with somebody,
and this was theirs and they used to stay there until
every night until 11...
Or 12, even midnight. We wouldn’t allow it,
but since it was a bomb shelter,
we couldn’t lock it,
so they were waiting for us to go to bed,
and they were going in...
sneaking back into the shelter. It was so important to them.
Being together...
Being with one another,
and that was something that we worked very hard on.
There were plenty of teenagers that at first
didn’t come,
didn’t even show up to the activities,
or the gatherings, so what we did, I instructed ...
the guides...
the youth guides that were with them.
I told them, "every different club",
"you take all the children,"
"the list, and you divide it between ... "
"Between the staff."
We brought huge staff to work with them and...
let's say that we had a twenty-something teenagers,
we brought four staff members,
and I divided the children between the staff members,
and I told them,
this is what you do, "you call every child every day",
"you’re not going to speak with them for half an hour",
"you’re going to say three sentences",
"we are at the club, we’re doing this and this today",
"we would be happy to see you."
That's it...
That's it, that's it. Every day.
And by december, it took time...
they were
coming and sniffing around
to see if it fits them or not,
by december we reached,
about 97% of attendance in the in the club,
but it was very hard work by the by the staff and...
another thing that I told them was,
"If you didn’t see a child for like the last month",
"and suddenly he appears, he must have a good experience",
so they were all on it,
they knew each one had the number,
the list of children, that they needed to focus on...
to make sure that they're not going,
to get lost somewhere,
because we did have many of them that broke down
so we were really monitoring.
We had this chart with monitoring
the children if you saw something
that needs to have a special attention,
and it was very important,
because we did have many of them that broke down
throughout the year.
And every person deals with trauma differently,
so I went way beyond your question,
This is something that is very important for me to say,
because I think that we found out
ways to deal with trauma that
In a situation that the world doesn’t really know,
there were very few researches
about this particular situation so...